so another Sut here is 1 book of 1 2 268
to
276 and it's about a person with the
Right View things that he's incapable of
doing so it says because it is
impossible there is no opportunity that
in that an individual accomplished in a
view could
approach any determination as permanent
SAR it's not possible it's possible that
puj could approach the termination is
permanent that is
possible it's impossible there is no
opportunity that an individual
accomplished in view soana could
approach any determination is
pleasurable it's impossible that he
could approach anything as
self it's impossible for him to take
away the life of his mother he could not
take away the life of his father and he
could not take away the life of an
arand with a corrupt mind he could not
shed the blood of the tagata he could
not split the S he could not acknowledge
another teacher that's not possible but
because it is possible that an ordin
person could do these
things so obviously this statement is
made by the Buddha who is much further
seeing than even the most accomplished
arand but certain things here can be
verified obviously for oneself without
needing Supernatural powers and so on to
see and uh those things are the
impossibility of taking any Sara is
permanent impossibility of taking any
Sara as pleasurable and impossibility of
approaching anything as s on account of
it why is that impossible well because
it has been thoroughly
understood thoroughly understood in a
sense that
um C these characteristics of
impermanence and
pleasure like suffering unpleasure
ability are the inherent characteristic
of some so in order to understand
impermanence and Dua you need to
understand what Saras are and you could
even see simply based on like how these
how the word SAR is translated in the
modern kind of Sut translations
there's many many views on on the topics
because it's a subtle thing to
understand and much more easier to
misunderstand so if you don't understand
what Saras are you will not be able to
then truly see impermanence and do on
the level where it needs to be seen for
you to get the right
View and another um another proof of
this is how often this very similar
passage that talks about sankara's
impermanence is completely misquoted
misunderstood misread even while you're
reading it like the Buddha never said
everything is impermanent everything is
suffering everything is not self he said
every Sara is impermanent every s is
suffering everything is not self as a
result of it
so it just seems like oh well there is
some difference but it's not a big deal
it's absolutely fundamental deal it's
like in the same sense with with ptit
but we won't get into P here now because
it's talking itself so the point is you
need to understand that there is a
difference between your sense of self
which is always on the level of that
dharm and things upon which sense of
self depends and that's what definition
of Sara is inseparable from determined
by hence the translation here is
determinations so for
example your mind state of I don't know
anger or let know let's take something
positive um elated happiness on account
of a prospect that you that you're
facing something something pleasant
coming your
way uh would you be a able to have that
mental state persisting would you be
able to be cherishing it Bound by it
enjoying it looking forward to
it if uh if your body were to
die if you were to die if something were
to happen to it if you were to stop
breathing your heart would to stop would
it be possible for you to even conceive
further experience of your sense domain
and pleasure and joy happiness and so on
without your life being a necessary
basis from which any sense experience is
inseparable from it's
impossible now see you recognize that
and you can even make sense of it even
when you hear it just like this oh yeah
of course yeah okay but it's not enough
to recognize it once or twice
because as the Buddha said and we
mentioned before ignorance is
beginningless which means you
cultivating the wrong view not seeing of
Sara not regarding them um impermanent
and unpleasurable but instead regarding
them as permanent and pleasurable
um you will then uh simply not be able
to to approve that just by seeing it
once or twice that's why as we said that
before Dharma cannot be done
accidentally you cannot stumble upon it
had this special experience that they
make you an AR hunt and so on needs to
be drilled repetitively that's what
would the meant it's it's like gradual
shelving of the sea takes time and
repetition or like wearing off the
handle of the axe and so on through
usage so that's why you cannot do it
accidentally because you need to keep
doing it and in order to keep doing
something you need to have have had
reason beforehand that it's worth doing and
beforehand that it's worth doing and
repeating and committing to it that's
the place of faith we covered that
before so in order for you to
then see the determinations as
impermanent you need to then accept the
presently Arisen experience of whatever
the mood is whatever feeling is whatever
perception is at the time and then then
see it as undermined see it as see it
undermined simultaneously by something
else that's there such as see the fact
that you're not in control over a life
in your body so to speak the life of
your body means that under Minds any
Prospect of your sense engagement your
life your career your family everything
you go through life is undermined by the
fact that you could not be alive next
moment and that's an unpleasant thing to
do to admit that to yourself
and that's where the training comes in
The Virtue that will prepare you to like
handle it and then Drilling and
reflection of of that contemplation and
recollec of death and so on so that's
basically you retraining yourself to not
regard your most fundamental Sara of
your body as permanent as
pleasurable because if you ignore that
you're then automatically regarding it
as permanent as pleasurable how well the
example I gave the the the joyful
Prospect you're looking to forward
forward to you don't question it you
take it for
granted so you take that as yourself as
your defining experience at the time
that you're going for and you don't
question it you don't even try to
reflect on it so what then happens to
that body which is there by the way you
cannot abandon Saras or replace them so
your body as a fundamental necessary
basis for any experience of the senses
elating experience or depressing doesn't
matter has has to be there but you're
not questioning you're not having a
second thought you're taking for granted
the elated experience that you presented
with you want it you crave it you
Delight in it you act upon it so what
happens to Sara
then well they put second they're not
seen as that because of which you are
able to have the experience they seen
that which is secondary which is sort of
subordinate to your related experience
in other words you put yourself first
and then these Saras then become tools
of yourself so instead of Saras
undermining your sense of self they will
then liberate you Saras become used by
the sense of self and that's when Saras
are regarded as permanent and
pleasurable so instead of impermanence
and discomfort of Saras undermining the
pleasurability of sense of self they get
to be seen through the pleasurability
gratus uously assume pleasurability of
the sense of self so that's why uh
that's why it's that opposing like you
need to see that which is permanent as
impermanent you need to see that which
you regard as pleasurable as not
pleasurable so you need to learn how to
see Saras for what they are as or rather
be able to admit to yourself that it's
fundamentally unpleasurable the fact
that you're not in control of your body
even if you can use it now for gaining
all the pleasure you want recognizing
the nature of of that discomfort that
impermanent I cannot own that will then
undermine your joy on that level of
sense of self but that's unpleasant so
people turn away from displeasure by
default which then makes you regard all
these obvious things that are not in
your control that are uncomfortable even
that elated pleasure that has arisen you
know that it cannot last in a like
forever in a sense of that you will
never experience pain again you know you
will but you take it for granted at the
face value then everything else is seen
through that pleasure of of that you
took for granted not other way around so
it's learning to turn that picture
upside down that's why you all the sutas
when the Buddha would teach down when
people would understand they would say
to him oh wow it's like turning that
which has been placed upside down
turning it bad rightly again that which
I used to put second is first now it
needs to be put first as second so
Sankara is a first you need to put him
as first as a necessary basis because of
which you wouldn't be able to have
experience of Joy nor pain nor anything
else in between
but if you start looking then at the
characteristics of this like what's the
characteristic of your presently living
enduring body right here right
now well you haven't had any say in its
arising you have no say in the its
organs operating you can use it you can
move it you can control it but
fundamentally in itself it's not in your
control recognizing that means seeing
determinations as impermanent so that's
where the right view is when you
recognize that to the extent sufficient
extent you have developed the Right View
you that's what soop part is and that's
why that person will be simply unable to
forget that because that is your very
core of your being of your thought of
your mind so it's not something that you
occasionally think and then you sort of
forget about
it so that's why aana will be unable to
approach for granted determination is
pleasurable in because determin for him
now signifies
impermanence determination now signifies
discomfort duka which that means any
experience cannot be taken
itself and as for taking away the life
of his mother father Aran blood of
tagata means intentionally he cannot
intentionally override the significance
of recognition of his mother he cannot
with a corrupt mind shed the blood of
the tar impossible like the significance
of that act is just inconceivable for
him who willingly consciously makes a
choice and and do that it's just
impossible he could not split the sa
impossible like willingly try to make
Schism is because he's part of it it's
just impossible or that he could
acknowledge another teacher that's not
possible either and that's literally so you have
either and that's literally so you have
arrived at uprooting the entire
existence through following the Buddhist
instruction so now that you can like
follow another teacher means now that
you can dismiss that and follow some
completely diametrically opposed
teaching it's impossible it's just
inconceivable because within that
diametrically opposed teaching you will
still see Saras are impermanent Saras
are uncomfortable everything else as a
result that depends upon them cannot be
taken itself thus you're still whatever
teaching other you see you're just going
to see it through the framework of
Dharma that you have understood and
that's why you become your own guide as
the other s to say nobody can be my
guide I'm My Own guide you have the
reference point the dhma eye as the
Buddha refer to that now can see oh this
is according to dhama this is not
according to the dharm and as the Buddha
said in another suta even if the whole
world comes to that person and says no
the Buddha is wrong um you should not
follow the Dharma he like you know he
might not say anything you know if if
they will harass him and so on but
internally it's impossible for him to to
basically agree with them it's just
impossible for him even if the whole
world tries to persuade him he will know
that the Buddha is right and the world
is wrong wrong cuz he verified it for
himself as simple as that